What should I do this summer?
今年的暑假怎么过呢？
Mai, you don't have a single thing planned for this summer?
小舞 你一点暑假计划都没有吗？
I have some plans.
有是有啦
Did I just rub salt in the wound?
爸爸是不是在你伤口上撒盐了？
You had plans with your boyfriend,
你原本是想跟男朋友去哪里玩的吧？
but you were dumped.
结果却被甩了
I wasn't dumped. We just broke up.
不是被甩 是和平分手
Oh, right.
好吧
Why are you doubting it?
你怎么就是不相信呢？
Did you really go out with that government worker who was two years older?
你真的跟那个 比你大两岁的公务员交往过吗？
Huh?
嗯？
It doesn't sound real.
怎么听起来一点都不真实？
Yes, I did. It wasn't my imagination.
是真的 不是我幻想的
I see.
那好吧
That was delicious. Thank you.
我吃饱了
Just leave it.
放着吧
-See you later. -Take care.
-我出门了 -路上小心
I have to find someone for her.
还是给她找个好对象吧
TOKYO DAIICHI BANK HEADQUARTERS
（东京第一银行本部 ）
BRANCH INSPECTION
（分行稽核班）
SOLO TRIP DURING SUMMER
（夏季单身独游）
This looks nice.
这看起来不错
Solo trip?
“单身独游”？
Good morning.
早安
Why are you looking at me with pity?
干嘛用这种可怜的眼神看我？
Hanasaki.
花琦啊
I hope you have a nice summer vacation… by yourself.
我祝你有个愉快的夏季旅行哦 孤零零的
What's wrong with going solo?
一个人去旅行又怎么了？
I can do what I want, like spend hours at a museum, keep the light on all night,
我爱做什么就做什么 去美术馆对着喜欢的画看几个小时
set the AC to my preference…
睡不着时可以亮着灯 还有可以调整我喜欢的空调温度…
The only ones who can talk about the perks of being alone are ones who've
只有那些有另一半的人才有资格
experienced being in a relationship.
论述单身狗的好处哦 花琦
I thought divorce
我以为离婚
meant failure.
就意味着失败呢
It's all about experience.
凡事都能成为经验 花琦
It's also important to avoid the worst case scenario.
避免最坏的结果也是非常重要的
What?
什么？
Good morning.
早
Is this a bad time?
怎么感觉气氛有点糟糕？
Not at all. Good morning.
完全没这回事 早安
-Good morning. -Morning.
-早安 -早
Is that a new inspection?
是新的案子吗？
Yes. Gotanda Branch. Incorrect payment and missing stamps.
对 是五反田分行 错误支出以及遗漏出纳印章
There's been lots of clerical errors lately, so please check on them.
最近好像老是出这种错 你们去查查吧
-Yes! -Ms. Hanasaki.
-好的 -花琦
Using 70% of your power should be good enough this time around.
这次你只要用七成功力就可以了
-What? -This is not a big issue.
-嗯？ -这不是什么大问题
Just come straight back after hearing them out.
问完话就立刻回来
Come straight back?
立刻？
I don't want you poking your nose where it does not belong,
要是你又多管闲事 插手不该管的事
only to dig up more problems.
发现更严重的问题可就不好了
Don't tell me the Gotanda Branch Manager belongs to…
难道说 这五反田分行的经理是…
The Shindo faction.
是真藤派的
I thought so.
我就知道
I see.
这样啊
It is a difficult time for Mr. Shindo.
真藤常务最近可不好过啊
What happened?
怎么了？
You don't know?
你不知道吗？
Mr. Shindo's rival for the next Presidency has appeared.
和真藤常务 竞争下任行长的对手出现了
Everyone in the bank is talking about it.
银行里每个人都在讨论呢
The battle for the next President…
行长之争啊
It sounds like something going on in a different company.
感觉像发生在其他公司的事一样
I agree. And who is Mr. Shindo's rival?
就是啊 那真藤常务的对手是谁呢？
Senior Executive Director Doujima. He came back from New York.
是刚从纽约回来的堂岛专务
I saw the article.
我看到报导了
Look.
看
Here.
这个
I see. This is Senior Executive Director Doujima.
所以这一位就是堂岛专务啊
EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR TSUYOSHI SHINDO
（常务执行董事 真藤毅）
SENIOR EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR SHOGO DOUJIMA
（专务董事 堂岛正吾）
Mr. Shindo.
真藤
Long time no see.
好久不见
Senior Executive Director Doujima.
堂岛专务 好久不见
You won't be able to do as you like from now on.
接下来可不会再让你任意妄为了
COMPANY NEWSLETTER
（《社内报导》）
I'm sure Mr. Shindo is pretty tense right now.
真藤常务现在想必是提心吊胆的吧？
Yes. Because it's whether he can become a President or not.
当然了 这可事关他能不能当上行长
He is facing a crossroad in his life.
简直就是站在人生最大的岔路口前
If she pushes a Branch Manager of the Shindo faction into a corner again…
要是她又把真藤派的分行经理 逼上绝路…
SECRETARIAL OFFICE ASSISTANT GENERAL MANAGER
（秘书室次长）
NAOKI KODAMA
（儿玉直树）
So scary.
好可怕
Hey you two, don't let fear get the best of you.
你们两也太杞人忧天了
Why worry about something that hasn't happened yet?
干嘛担心那些还没发生的事啊？
It's important to avoid the worst case scenario.
避免最坏的结果也是非常重要的
It's all about experience.
凡事都能成为经验啊
There now. Get along well, you guys.
行了 你们两个别吵了
TOKYO DAIICHI BANK
（东京第一银行）
There is a delicious minced meat cutlet restaurant around here.
这附近有家店 炸肉饼非常好吃
That sounds good.
听起来不错啊
I will treat you on the way back if--
-下班回家的时候请你吃吧 不过… -太棒了！
Listen to the end. If we can get back without facing any problems.
先把话听完 前提是你不能节外生枝
Don't worry, problems don't pop up left and right.
放心吧 一直以来都没什么大问题啊
I know, but…
话是这么说
Cutlet.
炸肉饼…
Why is she so confident?
真不知道她从哪儿来的自信
GOTANDA BRANCH
（五反田分行）
Hello. Thank you for waiting.
欢迎光临 让你久等了
Based on the interviews,
我们在会谈之后发现
we found out that the increase of clerical errors last month
上个月工作失误的增加 是由于出纳员正好在繁忙期请病假
is due to a shortage of workers since many tellers were out sick.
人手不足而导致的
I see.
是这样啊
Thank you for coming all the way from headquarters.
劳烦两位特地从本部跑一趟
Please don't worry.
没关系
You can request temporary clerical help.
你可以要求调配临时出纳员
Please let us know if you have any problems.
要是有困难 请随时联系本部
I will do that.
我会的
-Thank you very much. -Thank you.
-辛苦了 -谢谢
Thank you very much.
非常谢谢
You are very cheerful.
你还真有精神啊
Yes.
是的
I'm glad that there were no problems.
没有节外生枝 真是太好了
He was a calm person.
真是一位稳重的人啊
That's very rare for someone in the Shindo faction.
在真藤派里还真是少见
He smiled at us.
对我们也笑脸相迎
Of course even a person in the Shindo faction can smile…
就算是真藤派的人也还是可以笑…
He was the first one.
是第一次吧？
Let's go eat cutlets before we go back.
吃完炸肉饼就回家吧
You remembered that, huh.
你果然没有忘记
Hey, Matsuki.
喂 松木
Mr. Soma?
相马先生
I haven't seen you in so long. How are you?
好久不见 你还好吗？
Oh right, you're at the Gotanda Branch.
对了 你是五反田分行的
Yes. I wrote that on the New Year's card I sent.
对 我在今年的贺年卡上可是有写哦
That's right.
啊 想起来了
You never reply back to me.
可是我都没收到过你的回信呢
Well, I was thinking of doing it.
这个嘛 我有想过要寄给你的
-I'm sorry. -I am glad to see you here.
-真是抱歉 -不会 见到你很高兴
I'm Matsuki from the Finance Department.
我是融资课的松木
I'm Hanasaki from Branch Inspection.
我是分行稽核班的花琦
You came here for an inspection?
你们是来稽核的吗？
Yes. For the clerical errors. We're done now.
对 就是之前工作失误的事 现在要回去了
Mr. Soma, you're really an inspector, huh?
相马先生 你真的是稽核员啊？
Yes, of course.
当然了
It's hard to imagine.
真是难以想像
I worked under Mr. Soma at the Marunouchi Branch.
我在丸之内分行时是相马先生的部下
I see.
原来如此
He taught me all about loans.
他严厉地教导了我融资的基础呢
What's with that look?
你这眼神是什么意思？
Nothing.
没什么
So? Are there any problems?
所以你碰上什么麻烦了吗？
Yes?
嗯？
I heard you sighing.
我老远就听到你那叹气声了
Sorry.
抱歉
Um… Mr. Soma.
那个…相马先生
Do you have time?
不知两位有没有时间？
Huh?
什么？
I want your advice regarding a loan.
我有些融资方面的问题 想问问你
Well… I… don't…
这个嘛…我…
We have time. We were about to leave.
有时间啊 我们都要回去了
-Hey. -Really?
-喂 -真的吗？
Yes.
是的
AZUMIYA STORE
（安积屋商店）
This is Azumiya Store. I'm in charge of this customer.
这里是我负责的安积屋商店
They have three branches in the Shinagawa ward.
以品川区为中心一共开了三家店
This is their main store.
这里是总店
So what's the problem?
所以有什么问题？
Branch Manager suddenly told me to collect the 100-million-yen loan from them.
中北经理突然要我 回收他们融资的一亿日元
Collect 100 million yen?
回收一亿日元？
He said it's a branch decision.
他说这是分行的决策
Is it to prevent bad debts from occurring because
是由于这家店的经营有问题 为了避免不良债权
this store has some management issues?
才下此决定的吗？
No. They don't turn a huge profit, but they're in the black.
不是 虽然不是赚大钱 但这家店是有盈余的
If they are not in the red, then why?
明明没有亏损 为什么要这样做呢？
Branch Manager said that it has no potential.
经理说这家店没有发展潜力
But you don't think that way?
但是你并不认同？
Right.
是的
President Azumi.
安积社长
I see.
这样啊
AZUMIYA STORE PRESIDENT NAOTO AZUMIYA
（安积屋商店社长 安积尚人）
They won't change their stance?
方针无法改变吗？
I am very sorry.
真的十分抱歉
No.
没关系
I understand that it's not your fault.
我知道这不是松木你的错
You have been so good to us.
你总是设身处地为我们着想
No.
你客气了
But… your bank lent us the money,
但 你们银行让我们借了贷款
and they suddenly pull the rug from under us
突然又要收回去
without giving much thought to our situation.
完全不管我们这边的情况
Isn't this called "forcible collection"?
这样难道不是恶意回收贷款吗？
"Forcible collection."
“恶意回收贷款”
It's one of the phrases I hate.
这是我讨厌的词之一
But it seems that he has a reason to say that.
但他说的也有道理啊
Yes.
是
They're not in the red,
毕竟他们是没有过亏损
and they've never been behind on payments.
也不曾拖延还贷的公司
But we are trying to collect their loan all of a sudden.
我们却突然抽回融资
When is this due?
还款期限是什么时候？
End of this month.
这个月底
They have no time.
那时间不多了啊
I know.
是啊
What will happen to Azumiya Store if we forcibly collect 100 million yen
如果我们强行回收融资的一亿日元
and withdraw the loan?
安积屋会怎么样？
They will be in serious financial trouble.
肯定会陷入财政困境
Will they go bankrupt?
也就是说会破产吧？
Yes.
没错
Mr. Soma.
那个…相马先生
Will you please check Azumiya's credit file?
你能看看安积屋的信用记录吗？
Me?
我？
Yes. I want to get your opinion.
是的 我想听听你的见解
I can't do anything even if I see it.
我看了也帮不了什么啊
-We can't turn away now. -What did you say?
-我们不能袖手旁观 -连你都这样？
Please.
拜托了
-Mr. Soma. -I really need your advice.
-相马 -我真的很需要你的意见
Wait! Wait a second.
等一下…
AZUMIYA STORE
（安积屋商店）
What do you think?
怎么样？
The sales went down temporarily six months ago.
半年前有段时期的销售额下降了
Because a new supermarket opened around that time.
那时附近有家新超市开张
It's called Coming Mart.
对方叫未来超市
They are a big chain with 20 stores in the Kanto area.
是个在关东近郊 拥有20家店铺的大型连锁店
After they opened, Azumiya lost many customers.
店铺一开张 顾客就被抢了不少
So Azumiya had to cut prices in order to compete with them.
所以安积屋也只好降价来竞争
The customers are coming back now.
现在顾客回流了
As a result, they have as many customers now as they did before.
顾客量几乎恢复到和之前差不多
PROFIT RATIO
（利润率）
But the profit ratio…
但利润就…
They're buying at the same price, but selling at a discount,
他们进货价和之前一样 却低价出售
so they can't make a profit.
所以无利可赚
Right.
是的
That's why they need the funds right now.
所以他们非常需要周转资金
I think our branch should support mid-sized companies like Azumiya,
我认为银行 应该积极支援像安积屋这样
that have their main store location in Gotanda.
总店位于五反田的中小型企业
But I have to push them into bankruptcy.
但我却要做出 会让他们倒闭破产的事情
What are you doing?
你们在干嘛？
I thought the two of you left already.
你们不是回去了吗？
Well… yes…
那个… 有点事
AZUMIYA STORE
（安积屋商店）
Branch Manager, I asked Mr. Soma for some advice.
中北经理 是我拜托相马先生给我意见的
Why do you have to show this to people from Branch Inspection?
你为什么让分行稽核班看这些？
Mr. Soma was my boss at the Finance Department in Marunouchi Branch.
我在丸之内分行的融资课时 相马先生是我的上司
I asked him for advice on Azumiya.
我就问问他有关安积屋的事情
Are you still talking about that?
你怎么还说这样的话？
We're withdrawing the loan.
给我终止安积屋的贷款
Collect 100 million yen by the end of this month.
月底前回收那一亿日元 那是最后期限
Excuse me…
那个…
Breathe.
深呼吸
Why do you have to collect the loan all of a sudden?
为什么你突然要回收呢？
What?
什么？
They seem to be being put in a tight spot.
明明对方正处于财务困境
Do you think a loan is charity or something?
你是不是觉得贷款是件慈善事业啊？
It's business.
这是商业
But what you're doing is forcible collection.
但你这样是恶意回收贷款吧？
Forcible collection?
恶意回收贷款？
Are you criticizing my decision?
你是在批判我的做法吗？
No, I'm not criticizing. I just don't know the reason.
我不是批判 我只是想知道原因
I explained to Matsuki many times.
我跟松木说了好几遍了
That company is a loser.
那家公司是个输家
We'd rather finance a winner with better performance.
银行应该投资业绩好的赢家
That's a logical decision!
这是理所当然的商务信用判断
Excuse me for interrupting,
不好意思 打岔一下
but I also don't think there is an urgent need to collect the loan.
我并不认为 此刻必须如此紧急地进行贷款回收
How can you be so arrogant,
你仗著分行稽核班的身分
when you're only from Branch Inspection.
口气可真不小啊
Time always flies…
时间嘛
like an arrow.
是瞬息万变的
You're only a former Finance Department worker. What would you know?
你区区一个融资课的前职员 你知道什么？
You are a loser, too.
你也是个输家
You seem to have forgotten that.
看来你也忘记了这点
Listen.
听着
I, as the Branch Manager, will judge if this company is at risk or not.
我是银行经理 我会判断客户公司是否有风险
I will report this to headquarters.
我会向本部报告这件事
Yes.
是
RESTAURANT HANASAKI
（花琦居酒屋）
What's up with that damn Branch Manager?
那个混蛋经理算什么东西？
Hanasaki, watch your mouth.
花琦 别乱说
I want to kick myself for thinking that he was a nice manager.
之前还说他是什么笑脸相迎的好经理 我真想撞墙
You said, "He's rare for someone in the Shindo faction."
你还说：“在真藤派里还真是少见”
You said that, Mr. Soma.
那可是你说的 相马
Did I?
是我吗？
I am very sorry.
十分抱歉
Don't look so depressed. You're ruining our dinner.
别一脸郁闷的样子 糟蹋了我们美味的晚餐
You were humiliated because of me.
你会受到如此屈辱 都是因为我
It's okay. Don't worry.
没事啦 别放在心上
I said some unnecessary things too.
我自己也多嘴了
I am sorry that I made unnecessary remarks too.
抱歉 我也不小心插嘴了
No, no. It was my fault.
不 这全都怪我
Here's the ashitaba tempura.
这是明日叶的天妇罗 久等啦
-Thank you. -Thanks, Dad.
-谢谢 -谢谢 爸
You should try this. Everything here is delicious.
试试这个 这里的菜都超好吃的
Yes.
好的
I'll try.
我开动了
How is it?
怎么样？
-Delicious! -Thank you very much.
-好好吃 -谢谢
Mr. Matsuki.
那个…松木先生
May I ask you something? Are you married?
我想冒昧问你 你结婚了吗？
No, not yet.
还没
So you're single?
所以你是单身？
Yes.
是的
Hey!
喂
Dad, stop being rude. You haven't met him before.
爸 不要失礼啦 你们才第一次见面
Do you have a girlfriend by any chance?
顺便问一下 你有没有女朋友啊？
No.
没有
He's popular, but he's awkward.
这家伙很受欢迎 但是太笨了
Stop that.
你饶了我吧
He's handsome, but has a modest and nice personality.
明明是个帅哥 却很客气 性格很好
Drinks sake.
还很能喝
Dad…
爸
He's also a banker, who is single and free.
而且还是单身的银行职员
Everything about him is ideal. This must be destiny.
一切都那么理想 这只能说是命运了
We can hear what you're thinking.
爸 你的小心思我们都听到了
Mai, I will help you.
小舞 我会帮你的
First of all,
松木
what is your favorite food?
你喜欢吃什么啊？
Japanese-style omelet.
酱汁鸡蛋卷吧
I will make a special one right away.
我马上就给你做一份独一无二的
Thank you very much.
谢谢
Yes. Everything is going very well.
是的 一直都在顺利进行中
Things will be done soon.
很快就能办好的
AZUMIYA STORE
（安积屋商店）
President, regarding what we talked about earlier…
社长 关于上次那件事…
Come on. Stop sighing.
好了 别再叹气了
I'm sorry.
抱歉
I can't help it when I think of President Azumi.
我一想起安积社长的事就不自觉叹气
May I ask you something?
啊 可以问你一个问题吗？
What is it?
什么事？
Branch Manager said that
中北经理说了
he'd rather finance a winner with better performance,
与其贷款给业绩差的输家
than a loser with poor performance.
不如贷款给业绩好的赢家
Yes.
是的
If he thinks Azumiya Store is a loser,
如果对他来说安积屋商店是输家
what company does he consider to be a winner?
那怎样的公司才算是赢家呢？
There are several companies that he's keen on financing.
中北经理积极给予贷款的公司有几家
They are all big companies with financial power.
全都是资金雄厚的大企业
He is so obvious.
这也太好猜了吧？
One of them is Coming Mart.
其中一家就是未来超市
Is that the new store near Azumiya?
就是在安积屋附近的那家吗？
It's a competitor that came in six month ago.
就是在半年前开张的竞争对手？
Yes. It's so ironic.
是啊 很讽刺吧？
Are they doing that well?
那家店业绩真有那么好吗？
I'm not in charge, so I don't know well.
我不是负责人 所以我也不清楚
But personally, I can't bring myself to agree with their business strategy.
但是我个人并不认同他们的商业手段
What is it like?
例如呢？
They build a store near their competitors
他们故意在竞争对手附近开业
and make major discount sales for the first six months to make
并在开业的前半年疯狂大减价
their competitors withdraw.
逼迫对手从当地撤退
That's the strategy of big companies with financial power.
这是资金雄厚的大企业的手段啊
It may not be wrong business-wise,
这在商业上也许没错
but it's not fair.
但就是不太公平
I know.
就是说啊
I also don't understand the Branch Manager's complete opposite
我也不理解为什么 中北经理给予附近的竞争对手
lending stance towards the nearby competitor.
完全不同的贷款状态
We want to know more don't we, Mr. Soma?
真的让人很在意 是吧 相马？
Why don't we investigate Coming Mart?
我们调查一下未来超市吧
Yes. Let's investigate.
是啊 调查一下吧
TOKYO DAIICHI BANK
（东京第一银行）
COMING MART
（未来超市）
-Were you okay? -Yes.
-拿到了吗？ -是的
Here it is.
拜托了
Okay.
好
According to this paper, Coming Mart is not doing that well.
单看这个 未来超市的业绩也没那么好啊
-I agree. -Is that so?
-是啊 -是吗？
Look.
你看
The store in Gotanda is doing almost the same as Azumiya Store.
他们五反田分的数据 跟安积屋也没差多少
It seems like Azumiya Store is doing better than they thought,
看来是安积屋比想像中还要顽强
so they have to continue their discounts.
所以他们也不得不持续降价
I see.
原来如此
But the loan towards Coming Mart has drastically increased the last six months.
但是过去这半年里 拨给未来超市的贷款大幅度增加
It has reached the limit of 500 million yen.
甚至达到了上限五亿日元
That's huge.
那么多
The loan to Azumiya was 100 million.
安积屋的贷款才一亿日元吧？
I heard that he will be increasing the credit line.
我听说中北经理会再提高贷款上限
He sent a request to the Finance Department.
他已经向本部的融资部 提出了书面请求
Finance Department…
融资部…
Why is he this supportive towards Coming Mart?
为什么他对未来超市那么热心呢？
This makes it even harder to understand his decision.
我越来越搞不懂他的判断了
I don't understand why he brands
的确 我甚至想不通
Azumiya as a loser and Coming Mart as a winner.
为什么他认为安积屋是输家 而未来超市是赢家
I agree.
就是说啊
But there must be something that is making the Branch Manager do that.
肯定有什么内情 逼得中北径路这么做吧？
Something that isn't showing up among these numbers…
就是这组数字无法呈现的某种内情
What is that "something"?
那内情会是什么呢？
I don't know.
不知道
Thank you very much.
谢谢你们
No.
谢什么呢？
I haven't been able to help you out.
我们也没帮上什么忙
That's not true.
才不是呢
Mr. Matsuki.
松木先生
Isn't that President Azumi?
那不是安积社长吗？
President Azumi.
安积社长
Mr. Matsuki.
松木先生
I am visiting all the banks for a new loan request.
我去了各家金融机构申请贷款
But we're such a small company,
但我们这种突然来访的中小型企业
that they refuse us point blank.
他们根本就不理会
I don't think I can take it anymore.
或许已经到尽头了吧？
Goodbye.
再见
President Azumi?
安积社长
I'll call an ambulance.
我叫救护车
Please.
-拜托了
MEIKAI HOSPITAL
（名惠医院）
He was always proud of his health.
他还常常自夸自己的身体很健康
But he got cerebral anemia from fatigue.
却因为过度劳累而脑贫血
He was pushing himself too hard.
他太勉强自己了啊
This is because of our bank.
都是我们银行的错
Hanasaki.
花琦
I will go back to headquarters.
我要回本部
Okay.
喔 好的
Please stay here with Matsuki until Mr. Azumi wakes up.
你跟松本留在这里等安积社长醒来吧
Okay, I will.
知道了
Mr. Matsuki.
松本先生
Please don't get up.
你躺着吧
Sorry for causing you trouble.
不好意思 给你添麻烦了
No…
不会
What time is it now?
现在几点了？
It's almost three.
快3点了
I have to go to Mitsuba Shinkin.
我还得去三叶信用金融机构呢
Doctor said that you have to rest today.
医生说你今天得好好静养
I have no time to rest in bed.
我没时间躺在这里休养了
Please do as the doctor says, just for today.
请你听医生的话吧 一次就好
Why? Why is this happening?
为什么？为什么会这样？
What did my company do?
我的公司做错了什么啊？
I am sorry.
对不起
My late father built that company
我父亲生前白手起家
and worked hard to open up more locations.
勤勤恳恳地开了一家又一家店
There are customers who have been with us for two generations,
有的客人是两代人一直光顾我们
and those who ride their bicycles for 30 minutes to shop with us.
还有客人骑半小时自行车来到店里
Everyone says they come to my store because they love Azumiya.
大家都说会一直光顾我们 是因为喜欢安积屋
But why…
但是为什么…
I will go back to headquarters and talk to Mr. Soma about this.
我回本部和相马商量一下 看有没有什么办法
Thank you.
谢谢
I will try talking to the Branch Manager again.
我再和中北经理交涉一下
Will you be okay?
你可以吗？
Yes.
可以的
When it comes to loans, never give up
贷款工作没到最后都不要放弃
and do everything that you can.
要尽最大努力做好
That's what Mr. Soma taught me when I started working.
这是我刚入行时 相马先生教我的
Mr. Soma said that?
是相马教的吗？
When I was assigned to the Finance Department,
我被分到融资课后
I was very ambitious, and wanted big projects
野心勃勃 想着要做大手笔的工作
and to produce better results than my other colleagues.
要比同期进公司的人更早做出成绩
I always postponed the small companies.
那时我总是不把中小型企业当一回事
As a result, I once forgot to submit a request form in time
结果有一次我迟交书面请求
and a small printing company was about to go bankrupt because of me.
导致某家小印刷厂差点因为我而破产
But Mr. Soma negotiated with lots of people…
但是相马先生帮我去了很多地方交涉
Come on, apologize to them.
来 好好道歉
I am very sorry.
真的很对不起
Somehow we were able to pass the loan screening,
我们想办法让他们通过贷款审查
and the factory survived.
后来那间工厂就获救了
Mr. Soma did that…
相马吗？
Doing business with loans can crash a company,
贷款的工作可以毁了一家企业
and it can save a company in a pinch.
也可以救他们于水火之中
That's the first time I realized that.
那是我第一次体会到这点
I will never forget what Mr. Soma told me that time.
相马先生那时对我说的话 我这一辈子都不会忘记
What did Mr. Soma say?
他说了什么？
-Matsuki. -Yes.
-松木 -是
Banks deal with money
银行操纵的是钱
but we deal with people.
但接触的是人
Keep that in mind.
绝对不要忘了这点
Yes.
知道了
What he said has been supporting me.
他说的话成为了我的精神支柱
TOKYO DAIICHI BANK
（东京第一银行）
I have a question about a loan in Gotanda Branch.
我想问一下 有关五反田分行的某个贷款案件
GOTANDA BRANCH
（五反田分行）
I am back.
-辛苦了
AZUMIYA STORE REQUEST FOR LOAN EXTENSION
（安积屋商店 融资期限延长请求）
Come in.
请进
Excuse me.
打扰了
What is it?
什么事？
Will you please think about the loan extension for Azumi Store?
请你再考虑一下 延长安积屋商店的融资期限
You're still talking about that?
你还在说那事啊？
I have a question about your decision.
我对你的决定有疑惑的部分
Really?
是吗？
Why are you so eager to provide a loan for Coming Mart?
你为什么 对未来超市的融资如此积极呢？
Why do you care about Coming Mart?
你为什么那么关注未来超市？
Because your lending stance toward Coming Mart
那是因为你对未来超市的贷款态度
is the complete opposite of Azumiya Store.
和对安积屋的恰恰相反
You said that Coming Mart is a winner
你说过未来超市是赢家
and Azumiya Store is a loser.
而安积屋是输家
But…
可是
currently, these two stores have been performing equally.
目前这两者的业绩平分秋色
That is because you are overly committed to Azumiya.
-那是因为你在偏袒安积屋吧？ -不是
No. I am trying to be fair.
我是公平看待的
Then what?
所以你想怎样？
Do you want to say that I am making an unfair decision?
你是想说我在偏袒其中一方吗？
Yes.
没错
Fine.
好吧
I don't think you're suited for the Finance Department.
你好像不太适合融资部啊
Good luck in the world of losers.
你也不过是输家一枚呢
Get out.
出去
-You're back. -Yes.
-你回来了 -是
Mr. Azumi will stay at the hospital tonight.
安积社长今天会留院观察
I see.
好的
Mr. Soma.
相马
Isn't there anything we can do?
我们就没什么能做的事吗？
I went to the Finance Department.
刚才我去了融资部
I heard something very strange concerning Coming Mart.
打听到一件奇怪的事 是有关未来超市的
What?
什么？
-Is that true? -Yes.
-是真的吗？ -是的
The Finance Department plans to turn down the loan extension for Coming Mart.
融资部打算不通过 未来超市的增额贷款请求
Why?
为什么？
They aren't certain enough to approve the security and prospects of that company.
他们对那家公司的安全性和前景 不太有信心
Branch Manager Nakakita said that Coming Mart has possibilities, right?
可是中北经理说 未来超市很有发展前景啊
It looks like they are doing well because they open new stores
他们不断开分店 看起来经营得不错
but they're operating with debts.
但实际资金都是用借款维持着
They are in debt.
也就是说他们负债累累
So they don't have financial power.
所以他们并没有雄厚的资金实力
So now it's clear that Nakakita's credit decisions were not correct.
这就说明中北经理 对于批准贷款的判断是不正确的
Yes.
没错
But that won't be reason enough to stop him from collecting Azumiya's loan.
但这不足以成为 让他停止回收安积屋贷款的理由
Mr. Matsuki said that he would ask the Branch Manager again.
松木先生说他会去和中北经理交涉
What? It's going to be impossible!
什么？这肯定不行啊
He is as straight as an arrow.
那家伙真是耿直得像木头一样
It's because of you, Mr. Soma.
都是因为你啊 相马
Mr. Matsuki told me…
松木刚才跟我说…
I will never forget what Mr. Soma told me that time.
相马先生那时对我说的话 我这一辈子都不会忘记
Banks deal with money,
银行操纵的是钱
but we deal with people.
但接触的是人
Matsuki…
松木
He remembers such a thing.
那家伙还记得那事啊？
You have to take responsibility for him.
请你对他负起责任
You are responsible for making Mr. Matsuki a passionate banker.
是你让松木成为热情的融资员的
Mr. Soma.
相马
I think Branch Manager Nakakita is trying to collect the loan from Azumiya
我觉得中北经理是为了未来超市
for the sake of Coming Mart.
才要收回安积屋的贷款的
Why do you think so?
你为什么那么想？
Because Coming Mart's strategy is to
因为未来超市的作风
get rid of competitors near them.
就是铲除附近的竞争对手啊
Azumiya is hanging on a lot longer than they imagined,
因为安积屋比他们预期的还坚持
so they resorted to other means.
所以他们才会采取别的手段
Yes.
没错
Everything makes sense when you think about it that way.
这样想的话就合理了
Then…
那样的话
the reason why Branch Manager Nakakita supports Coming Mart is…
中北经理偏袒未来超市的理由是…
money?
钱？
Mr. Soma.
相马
Let's check Mr. Nakakita and Coming Mart's bank account.
我们调查一下 中北经理和未来超市的账户
-We might find evidence. -Okay.
-也许能找到证据 -好的
-You check Coming Mart.
-你负责未来超市
COMING MART PRESIDENT HIROMASA KAMIYA
（未来超市社长 神谷宏昌）
TOMOYASU NAKAKITA
（中北友康）
Please don't worry.
别担心
It's only a matter of time before Azumiya withdraws.
安积屋的倒闭只是时间问题
I see.
是吗？
COMING MART OPENING OF THE FIRST STORE
（未来超市 一号分店开幕）
Thank you very much.
谢谢你了
I knew I could count on you,
不客气
Branch Manager Nakakita.
不愧是中北经理啊
PRESIDENT OF COMING MART HIROMASA KAMIYA
（未来超市社长）
I am glad that we opened our store in Gotanda.
在五反田开分店果然是正确的
Thank you.
不敢当
By the way,
对了
are you open tomorrow?
明天下午你在吗？
Yes, I am.
在呢
I will drop by then.
我能过去一趟吗？
I want to say thank you.
我想当面感谢你
I will be waiting for you.
恭候你的大驾
We couldn't find anything after all.
果然什么都没有发现
Huh?
嗯？
I thought so.
我就知道
What is it?
发现了什么吗？
All of the transfers that Coming Mart makes,
未来超市的汇款对象
are to corporate accounts,
全部都是企业
except these, which are personal accounts.
除了这个私人账户
Eriko Taguchi?
田口惠里子？
AZUMIYA STORE
（安积屋商店）
KEN SOMA
（相马健来电）
-This is Matsuki. -Hey, where are you now?
-我是松木 -松木 你现在在哪儿？
What?
什么？
A dummy account?
假账户？
We checked the suspicious money flow from Coming Mart
我们调查了一下 未来超市可疑的资金流向
and found this personal account.
追溯到这个私人账户
This is a dummy bank account with an unknown account holder.
这个假账户的持有者并没有联系方式
Coming Mart is transferring money into this account?
所以未来超市一直往这个账户转账？
Yes.
是的
It's not limited to Coming Mart either. That account is receiving
不仅未来超市 这个账户也接收了
hundreds of thousands of yen from several big companies.
好几个企业转入的几十万日元
These are all customers of the Gotanda Branch.
这些都是五反田分行的客户
They're all companies the Branch Manager is providing loans to.
而且都是中北经理 积极给予贷款的公司
I thought so.
果然如此
Does this mean that Mr. Nakakita is receiving bribes through this account?
难道说中北经理 在用这个账户受贿赂？
Probably.
应该是这样
Mr. Nakakita is trying to crush Azumiya Store
中北经理收了未来超市的钱
in return for receiving money from Coming Mart.
打击并铲除安积屋商店
That's unforgivable.
真是岂有此理
Where are you going?
你要去哪？
I will ask him directly.
我要当面质问他
Wait a second.
等等
Even if you ask him now,
你现在去追问的话
he will deny everything saying that it's nothing but your assumption.
他肯定会否认 说那只是我们的推测
What should I do, then?
那我该怎么做？
Well…
这个嘛…
We need to get evidence that he is using this account, right?
我们要找到他在使用这个账户的证据
I see.
也对
If he has the passbook and the cash card for this account…
如果他拿着 这帐户的存折或提款卡的话…
Right.
没错
But do you think that we can check his bag?
你们以为我们有权力 检查他的随身物品吗？
No.
这行不通
But he's hiding it somewhere.
但他肯定藏在什么地方
Yes. He will be in big trouble if someone sees him
对 如果被人看见 他拿着别人名义的存折到处走
walking around with a passbook that has someone else's name on it.
那麻烦可就大了
That's right.
是啊
Somewhere close and safe?
有什么隐秘安全的地方呢？
In his drawer.
他的抽屉
I saw it earlier when I went to his room.
刚才我去他办公室时看到了
Excuse me.
打扰了
TOKYO DAIICHI BANK
（东京第一银行）
I saw him putting a passbook in the drawer.
我看见他把一本存折放进了抽屉
Was it from our bank?
是我们银行的吗？
Yes. When was this account opened?
是的 这个账户是什么时候开的？
Let me check. This is it, 1996.
我查查啊 这个 1996年
The design of his passbook is from that time.
他拿着的存折就是那时的设计
Bingo!
那就没错了
Yes.
是的
If we have that passbook…
如果我们拿到那本存折…
It'll be evidence.
就可以成为证据了
Yes, but we are not the police.
是 但我们又不是警察
We are not allowed to do such a thing.
我们没权利做这种事
That may be right, but…
话是这么说 但是…
That's the only way to save Azumiya Store.
这是拯救安积屋的唯一方法了
The problem is that the drawer is locked.
问题是…抽屉是锁着的
I'm sure he takes the key with him.
他肯定把锁匙带在身上
Maybe he has a spare key somewhere.
可能别处会有备用锁匙
No, he's managing it on his own.
没有 他都是自己保管
Oh, no…
这样啊
We may be able to find… the spare key.
说不定会有哦 备用锁匙
-What?
-什么？
TOKYO DAIICHI BANK
（东京第一银行）
No one is here yet.
还没有人来
Let's hurry.
快点
BRANCH MANAGER'S OFFICE
（分行经理办公室）
This is it.
就是这样
I knew it.
果然上锁了
-Let's find it. -Yes.
-找找看吧 -是
Mr. Soma, do you think it's really here?
相马 你真的觉得会有吗？
You said the spare key is probably in his room because
你不是说银行职员 习惯把重要的东西放在身边
bankers tend to hide important things close to them.
所以备用锁匙 很可能在他的办公室吗？
I said "probably." I didn't guarantee it.
我说“很可能” 又不是说一定有
Not fair.
不是吧？
-Did you find it? -Really.
-找到了吗？
It's so long.
好长啊
What is it?
这是什么？
A pen?
笔吗？
How misleading!
逗我呢
People will come to the office soon.
差不多快有人来上班了
Let's hurry up.
我们快点吧
-Hanasaki! -Sorry.
-花琦 -对不起
Look.
这个
What is it?
怎么了？
It fits.
对了
It turned.
打开了
Someone's coming.
有人来了
Is it the Branch Manager?
难道是中北经理？
Oh my God.
糟了
Please hide.
你们两个快躲起来
-Where? -Here!
-躲哪？ -这里啊
Only one person can fit.
只能躲一个人啦
BRANCH MANAGER'S OFFICE
（分行经理办公室）
It's okay.
没事了
-I was so nervous. -This is bad for my health.
-紧张死了 -这对心脏不好啊
Sorry.
不好意思
Okay. Let's do it.
没事 我们继续
TOKYO DAIICHI BANK ERIKO TAGUCHI
（东京第一银行 田口惠里子）
We found it.
-找到了
TOKYO DAIICHI BANK GOTANDA BRANCH
（东京第一银行五反田分行）
Are you sure I can have such an expensive gift?
我真的可以收下这么贵重的东西吗？
I had it specially made for you, Mr. Nakakita. Please take it.
这是为中北经理你量身订做的 请笑纳
A token of my appreciation.
这可是我的心意啊
Thank you very much.
十分感谢
Let's try it next month.
下个月有空吗？
I found a nice golf course.
我找到一个很好的高尔夫球场喔
Sounds great.
好啊
I wish to continue this business relationship with you.
今后也请你多多关照了
Me, too.
彼此彼此
Yes.
请进
Excuse me.
打扰了
Why are you guys here?
你们怎么来了？
Matsuki! What is this all about?
松木 这是怎么回事？
I came here to talk to Mr. Nakakita.
我们是来找中北经理你的
I have a guest here. Where are your manners?
没看见有客人在吗？多失礼啊
I want President Kamiya to listen to this too.
我们刚好也有话想问问神谷社长
I am Soma from Branch Inspection at Tokyo Daiichi Bank Headquarters.
我是东京第一银行分行稽核班的相马
I am Hanasaki.
我是花琦
President Kamiya, in order to get rid of your rival,
神谷社长 你为了击退你的竞争对手
Azumiya Store,
安积屋商店
you paid money to Branch Manager Nakakita and asked for his support.
用钱贿赂中北经理以得到他的帮助
Am I right?
我说得对吗？
That's ridiculous.
简直胡说八道
Branch Manager Nakakita.
而中北经理
You tried to collect the loan from Azumiya Store in return for the money.
你收了贿 要回收对安积屋的融资作为回报
How rude! I never did such a thing.
太失礼了 我怎么可能做这种事？
Here.
这个
This is a statement of a particular bank account.
是某个账户的金钱来往记录
ERIKO TAGUCHI
（田口惠里子）
In the last six months, Coming Mart made two transfers
未来超市在过去的半年期间
of one million yen each into this account.
给这个帐户 分两次汇入了每次一百万日元
That's two million yen in total.
总计二百万日元的款项
So what?
所以呢？
The name on this account doesn't actually exist,
这个账户的拥有者是伪造的
but the person using it
实际在使用账户的
is you, Mr. Nakakita.
是你 中北经理
It can't be…
这不可能
How dare you open my drawer without my permission?
你们怎么可以擅自打开我的抽屉？
I got permission from my boss.
我们已经取得了上头的许可
No, there must be some mistake.
不是 这一定有什么误会
I don't know about that account.
我不知道那个账户的事
Eleven more companies who are customers of Gotanda Branch
另外还有11家 五反田分行的客户企业
have transferred money into this account.
曾汇入款项到这个账户
And the person who has been eagerly providing loans to all of those companies,
而对这些客户企业 积极推进融资工作的人
is you, Branch Manager Nakakita.
也是你 中北经理
You received money from them
你收了他们的钱
and gave them special treatment.
让他们优先获得融资 对吧？
No.
不是的
If you don't admit it now,
要是你现在不承认的话
we will ask the businesses you had dealings with.
我就得去每一家企业问个明白了
You should honestly admit it
你就老实承认吧
if you have pride as a banker.
保留一点银行家的自尊心啊
President Kamiya,
神谷社长
have you ever worked in your store?
你试过站在自家店门前上班吗？
Whenever President Azumi has spare time, he works at his store,
安积社长他只要有时间 都会站在店里
to listen to his customers,
听客人说话
so that he can improve his store.
再回馈到商店经营中
I think that is why Azumiya has been loved by the locals,
正因为如此 安积屋才能经历那么长的时间
for such a long time.
依旧受到当地人的喜爱
But you are trying
可是你
to crush his store by using these dirty tricks.
却想用这种肮脏的手段去铲除它 你真是…
You have failed as a businessman.
你真是不配当一个生意人啊
Excuse me.
我先失陪了
President!
社长
What a mess!
怎么会这样？
This is all because of that loser company.
都怪那个输家
With all due respect…
请恕我直言
I don't think Azumiya is a loser.
我并不认为安积屋是输家
First of all, what is a loser and a winner?
我们要如何定义赢家和输家呢？
You have no right to decide that!
你根本就没资格擅自断定
What?
你说什么？
Mr. Matsuki is working hard to extend Azumiya's loan
松木先生为了安积社长
to save President Azumi.
拼命延长安积屋的融资
On the other hand,
而你
you are working to provide loans for Coming Mart,
却为了自身利益
to get money for yourself.
帮助未来超市获取融资
-Shut up! -No, I won't.
-住嘴！ -我不要
Banks deal with money,
银行操纵的是钱
but we deal with people.
但接触的是人
Mr. Matsuki took those words to heart,
松木先生一直带着这句教诲
as he continued to work providing loans.
继续做着融资的工作
I don't know much about loans.
我不太懂融资的事情
However,
但是
people who only think of money shouldn't hurt people
眼中只有钱的人伤害了那些
who are working for the people. That's wrong!
以人为本在工作的人 这是大错特错
There were illegal dealings behind your loan screening for Azumiya.
你带着不正当的理由 进行对安积屋融资的判断
What you have done is completely unforgivable as a banker.
身为银行职员 你的所作所为是绝对不被允许的
Please cancel the loan collection.
请撤回回收融资的决定
AZUMIYA STORE
（安积屋商店）
-Really? -Yes.
-真的吗？ -是的
We cancelled the collection of one million yen.
回收一亿贷款的决定已经取消了
Please let us continue the loan as before.
你们将一如既往地获得融资
Thank you.
谢谢你
I am so glad that you are in charge.
能和你合作真是太好了
Let's continue working together.
彼此彼此 今后也请多多指教
Thank you.
多多指教
Do you need a tissue?
要纸巾吗？
Shut up.
闭嘴
Mr. Soma must have been a great boss
你一定是个好上司
to have raised such a wonderful subordinate.
才会培育出这么好的部下
I was just lucky.
我只是幸运遇上了好部下
And look what I have now.
不过现在就…
What do you mean?
你什么意思啊？
Nothing.
没什么
Mr. Nakakita received a disciplinary dismissal, huh.
中北经理被解雇了吗？
It's reasonable.
很合理吧？
Branch Inspection did a great job.
是分行稽核班的功劳啊
I'm so glad.
真是太好了
You can't be happy for long.
用不着这么高兴
At least, Mr. Shindo is not happy about this.
至少真藤先生高兴不起来
Mr. Nakakita was in the Shindo faction.
对啊 中北经理是真藤派的
The Branch Inspection duo
真没想到分行稽核班那两个人
may have unintentionally caused a stir with the battle for the next Presidency
不经意地卷入了真藤常务和堂岛专务
between Mr. Shindo and Mr. Doujima.
争夺下届银行行长的事呢
That's my guess.
是吧？
DISCIPLINARY DISMISSAL
（解雇惩处）
The Branch Inspection did something unnecessary again.
分行稽核班又来给我们添乱了
Something unnecessary?
添乱？
Yes, sir.
是的
He was a Branch Manager whom you favored…
中北经理曾是你关照的分行经理…
-Mr. Kodama. -Yes?
-儿玉 -是
I have nothing to do with a man named Nakakita.
我不认识什么中北啊
Am I right?
对吧？
Sure. I was wrong.
当然了 是我搞错了
-I think so, too. -Yes, sir!
-我想也是呢 -是的
It's delicious.
好好吃
I can tell you really like it.
看得出来你真的很喜欢啊
I'm so happy because I'm finally able to eat this.
终于吃到这个了 好高兴哦
Thank you very much.
真的很谢谢你
I will never forget what you and Mr. Soma did for me.
我不会忘记相马先生和你的恩情的
Stop that. Plus, you treated me to this.
好了 你已经请我吃这个了
I admire you, Ms. Hanasaki.
花琦小姐 你好厉害啊
You have a strong will and firm attitude.
你那坦率的想法 坚定的态度
I have to be like you.
我也想像你一样
Not at all.
哪有？
Mr. Matsuki, you were cool too.
松木先生 你也很帅哦
-Um… Ms. Hanasaki. -Yes?
-那个… 花琦小姐 -是
There is a restaurant near here that serves delicious cured meat.
这附近有家很好吃的牛排店
-Would you like to come with me? -Yes.
-你有兴趣一起去吗？ -好啊
Really?
真的吗？
Yes, I would love to.
真的 我很乐意
-Mr. Soma! -What's up?
-相马 -怎么了？
Mr. Matsuki says he will take us to a restaurant with cured meat.
松木先生说 想带我们去一家很好吃的牛排店
Matsuki?
松木吗？
What?
不会吧？
I was asking for a date.
人家原本打算两人约会的说
Is that the famous one near here?
就是这附近很有名的那家店吗？
-Yes. -Thanks, Matsuki.
-是的 -谢谢你啦 松木
This is the one.
就是这家
It looks delicious.
看起来好好吃啊
Yes, it is.
对啊 很好吃的
I'm sure it is.
肯定好吃
A5 ranked Japanese Black. It sounds great.
高级和牛 听起来不错啊
I can't wait.
好期待哦
Three million?
三百万日元？
Was it embezzled?
难道是盗用？
Are you saying that we hid it?
你是说有人故意把现金藏起来了吗？
Cash leaves no trail.
现金不留痕迹
We have to catch that moment.
我们一定要抓住那个瞬间
Why did you go that far?
为什么要做到这个地步呢？
I can finally end it here.
这下子终于结束了
I will not forgive you.
我绝对不会原谅你